Guide to the Robert Ralph Young Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Robert Ralph Young papers
1909-1985
MS 1738
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
10
The papers consist of correspondence, business files, autobiographical and other writings, photographs and other materials documenting the business career and personal life of Robert R. Young. The collection documents Young's efforts to take control of the Alleghany Corporation and the New York Central Railroad. The papers also include materials concerning the lives of his wife, Anita O'Keeffe Young, and his daughter, Eleanor Young.
Young, Robert R., 1897-1958
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Wallace, 1998.
Biographical / Historical
Robert Ralph Young was born February 14, 1897 in Canadian, Texas, the son of David John Young, president of the First National Bank of Canadian, and Mary Moody. He graduated from Culver Military Academy in 1914 and attended the University of Virginia. After leaving the University in his second year, he married Anita O'Keefe, sister of painter Georgia O'Keefe. They had one child, Eleanor Jane Young, who died in 1941.
A businessman of distinction, Young began his career working for E. I. DuPont de Nemours Company. He later held positions in the financial departments of the Allied Chemical Corporation (1916-1920) and General Motors Corporation (1922-1928). He left General Motors in 1928 to become a financier, serving as chief financial advisor to John J. Raskob. In 1929 he formed the successful brokerage firm of Young, Kolbe, and Company. A conflict between the two partners resulted in the dissolution of the company in 1937.
Young and a group of investors purchased the Alleghany Corporation in 1937. The ailing holding company of Oris and Mantis Van Sweringen held interests in coal mines, trucking companies, over 23,000 miles of railroad tracks, and railroads, most notably the Chesapeake Ohio, Nickel Plate, and Missouri Pacific. He soon became known for his opposition to the control of railroad finance by investment banks.
The first of many battles between Young and the investment bankers began soon after he purchased the Alleghany Corporation. In 1937 the Guaranty Trust Company of New York impounded all income and surplus of the Chesapeake Ohio Railroad. Young fought the trust for control of the company he had purchased. The resulting proxy contest ended in a compromise winning Young a position on the board of directors. The battle began again in 1938 when the Chesapeake Ohio Railroad's bonds were up for renewal. Going against the long standing tradition of control by the investment bankers, Young inaugurated the policy of competitive bidding in the financing of railroad securities.
Young's most famous battle for a railroad began in 1946 when he started buying stock in the New York Central Railroad. Using the Alleghany Corporation and the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad, Young purchased enough shares to make them the largest stockholders in the company. Young demanded and acquired a position on the New York Central Railroad's board of directors. He later was forced to give up his seat on the board when the Interstate Commerce Commission ruled that his positions on the Alleghany and Chesapeake Ohio boards represented a conflict of interest. Young was temporarily defeated in his attempt to take control of the New York Central.
Young continued to purchase stock in the New York Central Railroad until 1954, when he and his partner, Allen Kirby, became the largest stockholders. He also controlled the stock purchased by Alleghany and the Chesapeake Ohio. After resigning from the Alleghany and Chesapeake Ohio boards, Young demanded control of the New York Central Railroad. The board of directors refused his demands, resulting in proxy contest. The proxy contest for the New York Central Railroad remains one of the most notable proxy contests in American railroad history. Young initiated a media blitz that resulted in his winning control of the railroad by over a million shareholder votes. He took over as director and chairman of the board in 1954.
Robert Young cultivated the image of an outsider opposing Wall Street bankers. His lasting legacy was the initiation of competitive bidding for railroad securities and his masterful use of the proxy contest. Young died by his own hand in 1958.
The papers document the professional career and personal life of businessman Robert R. Young. The collection includes business files that document Young's takeovers of the Alleghany Corporation and the Chesapeake Ohio and New York Central Railroads. The collection also includes a substantial amount of writings. His unpublished autobiography chronicles his childhood, early adulthood, and to a lesser extent, his business career. Young's views on business and other economic matters can be ascertained from his essays, articles, speeches, and statements before Congress. Young's personal papers consist mostly of correspondence to and from relatives and friends. The bulk of the correspondence consists of letters from Young's daughter, Eleanor. Her letters span thirteen years and document the life of a young socialite in the 1930s and 1940s. Also included are a substantial number of photographs of Young, his family, and friends.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, business files, autobiographical and other writings, photographs and other materials documenting the business career and personal life of Robert R. Young. The collection documents Young's efforts to take control of the Alleghany Corporation and the New York Central Railroad. The papers also include materials concerning the lives of his wife, Anita O'Keeffe Young, and his daughter, Eleanor Young.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in four series: I. Business Files, 1929-1974. II. Writings, ca. 1930s-1950s. III. Personal and Family Papers, 1909-1985. IV. Audio/Visual Material, ca. 1900s-1950s.
Proxy -- United States; Railroad companies -- United States; Railroads -- Management; Wheeler, Burton K. (Burton Kendall), 1882-1975; Young, Anita O'Keeffe; Young, Eleanor Jane; Young, Robert R., 1897-1958; Alleghany Corporation; Atina Corporation; Chesapeake and Ohio Railway Company; Equishares Corporation; New York Central Railroad Company; Young, Kolbe & Company
- Business Files, 1929-1974; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series documents Young's thirty-year business career but should not be considered comprehensive. The series is arranged chronologically, reflecting Young's association with the following companies: Equishares Corporation; Steele Investors Incorporated; Atina Corporation; Young, Kolbe and Company; Alleghany Corporation; and New York Central Railroad Company.
  Files documenting the Alleghany Corporation comprise the bulk of the series. They include reports outlining the history of the company, as well as its acquisition by Young. The reports also include copies of pertinent documents related to Young's association with the company, such as purchase agreements and correspondence. The 1938 proxy contest for control of the Chesapeake Ohio Railroad is extensively documented with correspondence, proxy solicitations, memoranda and field reports, and a lengthy article by Young. The Alleghany files also contain material related to the congressional investigation on railroad financing. Included are several congressional reports on the Alleghany Corporation and transcripts of statements by Young before Congress.
  Another significant portion of Business Files pertains to the proxy contest for control of the New York Central Railroad. This section is comprised of the correspondence between Randolf Phillips, of the Alleghany Corporation, and Harry Heller, of the Interstate Commerce Commission, the policing agency in proxy contests. The correspondence consists of letters requesting approval of solicitations, drafts of solicitations to New York Central stockholders, and advertisements designed to win Young public and shareholder support in the proxy contest. Also included in this section is a transcript of Young's statement before Congress on proxy contests in general.
  Files pertaining to the first four companies consist primarily of routine correspondence regarding business agreements and transactions. Clippings representing ten years of media coverage of Young's business affairs are arranged chronologically and are listed at the end of the series. Most of the articles pertain to the proxy contests for the Chesapeake Ohio and the New York Central Railroads.
  - Equishares Corporation [correspondence], 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Steele Investors Incorporated [correspondence], 1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Atina Corporation [Broseco Corporation account]
    - Contracts, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1931-1936 (Box 1, Folder 5-10)
  - Young, Kolbe and Company [Allen Kirby account]
    - Account statements, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence
      - Kirby, Allen and companies, 1935-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-20)
      - Central Hanover Bank Trust Company, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Alleghany Corporation
    - Bylaws, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Congressional hearings
      - Reports, congressional, 1940, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Statements of Robert R. Young, 1946, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
      - Statement of Robert W. Purcell, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence, 1937-1954 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Exchange offers, 1952, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
    - Interstate Commerce Commission applications, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Lawsuits
      - Alleghany v. James Foundation
        - Brief, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 31)
        - Depositions, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 32)
        - Memoranda, 1952, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Zenn et al v. J. J. Anzalone et al
        - Notice of hearing, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 34)
        - "Suggested answers...,", 1953 (Box 3, Folder 35)
        - Testimony of David Wallace, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 36-37)
        - Testimony of Robert R. Young, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 38-41)
    - Missouri Pacific Railroad, 1946, 1966, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Reports
      - General, 1937-1940, undated (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - "Alleghany Corporation," 1939 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - "Campaign of the Chesapeake and Ohio Lines for Better Sleeping Car Service: A Review of Releases and Reaction by the Public and Press," ca. 1946 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - "Purchase by Messrs Young, Kolbe...," n.d. (Box 3, Folder 46-48)
      - "Twenty Years of Stewardship," n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49-51)
      - "Working Draft...Alleghany Annual Report," [1953] (Box 4, Folder 52)
    - Proxy contests
      - General, 1955 (Box 4, Folder 53-54)
      - Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad
        - Correspondence [with stockholders], 1938 (Box 4, Folder 55-59)
        - Memoranda and reports
          - General, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 60-63)
          - "100,000 Word Article" by Robert R. Young
            - Text, undated (Box 4, Folder 64-67)
            - "Exhibits," n.d. (Box 5, Folder 68-71)
        - Stockholder lists, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - New York Central Railroad [proxy contest]
    - Correspondence
      - 1954 Feb-Apr (Box 5, Folder 73-82)
      - 1954 May (Box 6, Folder 83-88)
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1957 (Box 6, Folder 89)
    - Report, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 90)
    - Statement before Congress [re: proxy contests], 1955 (Box 6, Folder 91)
  - Clippings
    - 1937
      General note
      See: Oversize, folder 1
    - 1938 May-1939 August (Box 7, Folder 92-100)
    - 1939 September-1942, 1953-1958 (Box 8, Folder 101-108)
- Writings, Circa 1930s-1950s; Series II
  Writings is arranged alphabetically within three sections: autobiographical, essays and articles, and poetry. The autobiographical writings include three unpublished autobiographies. The most detailed, "Autobiography in Three Parts," includes three versions of Part I, "Punk." Young provides detailed descriptions of his boyhood in Canadian, a small Texas town. Young describes escapades of hunting, primary school, his days at Culver Academy, and his two years at the University of Virginia. Part I ends when Young marries Anita O'Keefe and begins his business career. In a less detailed manner, Parts II and III chronicle the 1910s to the 1940s and describe his business career including his time at a DuPont plant, his interest in the stock market, his relationships with various business associates, and his business ventures. The proxy battles for the Chesapeake Ohio and New York Central Railroads are not covered in the autobiographies. In Young's original conception of his autobiography, Part II was to be narrated by Eleanor, his deceased daughter and titled "Nell." The file, "Nell" includes rough drafts for this unused version of Part II and is listed at the end of the Autobiographies section.
  Essays and Articles primarily relate to Young's ideas and experiences with business and finance. Included in this section is a manuscript of "Essays in Enterprise" in two parts, edited by Dr. Charles A. Welsh. Part I of the manuscript consists of Welsh's introduction describing Young's significance to the business world. Part II is Welsh's compilation of essays, articles, and speeches by Young on various subjects including the railroad industry, finance, and world affairs.
  One folder of incomplete bibliographies of Young's writings, speeches, and statements is listed at the end of the series.
  - Autobiographical writings
    - "Autobiography in Three Parts"
      - Part I, "Punk 1897-1916"
        - Draft A, undated (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
        - Draft B, undated (Box 9, Folder 4-6)
        - Draft C, undated (Box 9, Folder 7-10)
      - Part II, undated (Box 9, Folder 11-12)
      - Part III, 1956 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - "First Fifty Years,", Circa 1947 (Box 10, Folder 14-19)
    - [Untitled], 1947 (Box 10, Folder 20-23)
    - "Nell,", undated (Box 10, Folder 24)
  - Essays and articles
    - General, ca. 1940s-1950s, undated (Box 10, Folder 25-26)
    - "Essays in Enterprise," [edited by Dr. Charles A. Welsh]
      - Part I, undated (Box 10, Folder 27-28)
      - Part II, undated (Box 11, Folder 29-37)
  - Poetry, ca. 1930s-1950s (Box 11, Folder 38-40)
  - Bibliographies, undated (Box 11, Folder 41)
- Personal and Family Papers, 1909-1985; Series III
  Arranged alphabetically, the series consists of biographical material, correspondence, financial records and memorabilia documenting the personal life of Robert R. Young and his family. The bulk of the series is comprised of correspondence to and from Young that is arranged alphabetically. The correspondence includes a substantial number of letters from his daughter, Eleanor, that span twenty years and document her life as a young socialite. A few letters from Young to his daughter are also included. One folder of general correspondence is listed at the beginning of the section, and one folder of correspondence related to Young's 1947 trip to Texas is listed at the end of the section.
  The series also includes files relating to members of Young's family. The Anita Young files include correspondence and legal papers relating to a challenge of Robert Young's will by his siblings. One folder of correspondence from genealogist Ella Durfee to Anita Young regarding the Young lineage is included in this section. The Eleanor Young files are comprised of vital and school records. One file of biographical material on Young's father, David, is also included in this section.
  - Biographical material
    - General, 1941, 1947 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Clippings, 1937-1958, undated (Box 12, Folder 2-6)
      General
      See also: Oversize, folder 8
      See also: Oversize, folder 7
  - Correspondence
    - A-Z (general), 1938-1954 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Exum, Edith, 1947-1958, undated (Box 12, Folder 8-11)
    - Exum, Frank, Jr., 1954-1955 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Exum, Frank, Sr., 1948-1957, undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Exum, Robert, 1954, 1956 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Hartman, Charles, 1950-1953 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Hoover, Ed, 1944-1957, undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - James T. White Company [re: inclusion of biographical sketch of Young and his father in encyclopedia], 1941-1942 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Studer, Floyd, 1952 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Wheeler, Burton and Edward, 1937, 1948-1957 (Box 12, Folder 19-20)
    - Young, Anita, undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Young, David, 1927 (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Young, Eleanor
      - Holographs
        - 1927-1936 (Box 13, Folder 23-38)
        - 1937-1947, undated (Box 14, Folder 39-51)
      - Transcriptions, 1927-1941 (Box 15, Folder 52-59)
    - Young, Kenneth, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 60)
    - Trip to Texas, 1947-1948 (Box 15, Folder 61)
  - Diary [one notebook], 1942-[1946] (Box 15, Folder 62)
  - Financial records
    - Accounts ledgers
      See: Oversize, folders 3-6
    - Income tax returns
      - Memoranda, 1925-1929, 1944 (Box 15, Folder 63)
      - Federal
        See: Oversize, folder 10
      - State, 1922-1927, undated (Box 15, Folder 64)
      - Stocks [correspondence and statements], 1924-1929 (Box 15, Folder 65)
  - Memorabilia
    - Auction catalogue, 1983 (Box 16, Folder 66)
    - Culver Academy
      - Graduation banquet, 1914 (Box 16, Folder 67)
      - Yearbooks, 1913, 1914 (Box 16, Folder 68-69)
    - Diploma
      See: Oversize, folder 9
    - Honor ("Texan of Achievement"), 1947 (Box 16, Folder 70)
    - Resolutions, 1958 (Box 16, Folder 71-72)
  - Young and Moody families
    - Clippings
      See: Oversize, folder 2
    - Genealogical material, 1921, 1947 (Box 17, Folder 73)
  - Young, Anita (wife)
    - Correspondence [incoming and outgoing]
      - General A-Z, 1932, 1958-1959 (Box 17, Folder 74)
      - Durfee, Ella, 1944-1952 (Box 17, Folder 75)
      - Exum, Edith, 1948, 1958-1959 (Box 17, Folder 76-77)
      - Hoover, Ed, 1958, 1962 (Box 17, Folder 78)
      - Young, John family of, 1958-1959, undated (Box 17, Folder 79)
    - Lawsuits, 1964-1965 (Box 17, Folder 80-81)
    - Miscellaneous, 1937, 1941 (Box 17, Folder 82)
  - Young, David (father), 1917-1944 (Box 17, Folder 83)
  - Young, Eleanor (daughter), 1918-1939 (Box 17, Folder 84-85)
- Audio/Visual Material, Circa 1900s-1950s; Series IV
  The series is arranged alphabetically by format and includes film, phonodiscs, and photographs. One film depicts the events surrounding the New York Central shareholders meeting held in Albany, New York in 1954, including footage of press conferences and scenes of Young talking with shareholders prior to the meeting. No footage of the meeting itself is included. Also in this section are three reels of footage of a vacation cruise Young took around 1951. The quality of the vacation film is poor with no sound and is of little value to researchers.
  The phonodisc section consists of radio coverage of the 1954 New York Central shareholders meeting with brief interviews of Robert Young and William White, President of the New York Central Railroad. The section also includes a disc of scripted interview answers regarding the proxy contest for the New York Central Railroad and recordings of radio broadcasts sponsored by the Chesapeake Ohio and New York Central Railroads.
  The original films and audio recordings may not be viewed or played. For more information on copies created for research use consult the Audio Recordings and Film appendices.
  The bulk of the series consists of photographs documenting the personal life and career of Robert R. Young. The photographs are divided into personal and business photographs. Arranged alphabetically by subject, most of the personal photographs consist of portraits and candids of Robert R. Young, his wife Anita O'Keefe Young, and his daughter Eleanor Young. Photographs of Young's 1947 trip to Texas comprise a significant portion of the section. Also included are several photographs of the Duke and Duchess of Windsor, who were friends of the Youngs. One folder of miscellaneous and unidentified photographs is listed at the end of the section. Business photographs are also arranged alphabetically by subject. The photographs document the New York Central shareholders meeting, at which Young won control of the railroad, and Young's personal appearances at various engagements. The Associates file includes a photograph of the New York Central board of directors and photographs of Clint Murchinson and John J. Raskob.
  - Film
    Conditions Governing Access
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - "Television Coverage of Mr. R. R. Young, New York Central Campaign", 1954 (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Vacation footage (Elpetal cruise), Circa 1951 (Box 19, Folder 2-4)
  - Phonodiscs
    - "C O News Summary with Tris Coffin" (news program sponsored by C O Railroad), 1953 November 18 (Box 20, Folder 5-6)
    - "C O News Summary Reported by Tris Coffin" (news program sponsored by C O Railroad), 1953 December 23 (Box 20, Folder 7-8)
    - "M. S. Rukeyser Broadcast New York Central Stockholders Meeting", 1954 May 26 (Box 20, Folder 9)
    - "New York Central Jim Conway Show" (broadcast sponsored by New York Central Railroad), 1954 June 18 (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - "Questions and Answers by Robert R. Young" (transcript included), [1954] (Box 20, Folder 11-12)
  - Photographs
    - Personal
      - Exum, Edith and family, 1950s, undated (Box 21, Folder 13)
      - [Relatives, mostly unidentified], 1940s, undated (Box 21, Folder 14)
      - Texas (house where Young grew up), undated (Box 21, Folder 15)
      - Travel
        - Elpetal cruise, Circa 1950 (Box 21, Folder 16-19)
        - Texas trip
          - General, 1947 (Box 21, Folder 20-22)
          - Banquet, 1947 (Box 21, Folder 23)
          - Hunting, 1947 (Box 22, Folder 24-26)
      - Windsor, Duke and Duchess, Circa 1940s-1950s (Box 22, Folder 27-28)
      - Young, Anita, Circa 1910s-1950s (Box 22, Folder 29-30)
        See also: Oversize, folder 13
      - Young, David, undated (Box 22, Folder 31)
      - Young, Eleanor, 1920s-1940s (Box 22, Folder 32-35)
      - Young, John family of, 1945 (Box 22, Folder 36)
      - Young, Robert
        - As a child and young adult, circa 1900, circa 1920 (Box 23, Folder 37)
        - Newport and beach scenes, 1950s (Box 23, Folder 38)
        - Playing golf, 1950s (Box 23, Folder 39)
        - Portraits, 1940s-1950s (Box 23, Folder 40-42)
          See also: Oversize, folders 14-18
        - With family, 1930s-1950s (Box 23, Folder 43)
        - With others, 1950s (Box 23, Folder 44)
        - With rifle, Circa 1940s-1950s (Box 23, Folder 45)
        - With the Windsors, 1950s (Box 23, Folder 46-47)
      - Miscellaneous and unidentified, Circa 1930-1950s (Box 23, Folder 48)
    - Business
      - Associates, 1940s-1950s (Box 24, Folder 49)
      - Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad, 1947, undated (Box 24, Folder 50-51)
      - New York Central Railroad, 1950s (Box 24, Folder 52-56)
        See also: Oversize, folders 11-12
      - Personal appearances, 1947-1954, undated (Box 24, Folder 57-62)